<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pair-programming | Rails on Maui]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.railsonmaui.com//blog/categories/pair-programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.railsonmaui.com//"/>
  <updated>2015-10-20T19:12:30-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.railsonmaui.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Gordon]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[justin@railsonmaui.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remote Pair Programming Tips using RubyMine and Screenhero]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.railsonmaui.com//blog/2014/05/06/remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T22:36:22-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.railsonmaui.com//blog/2014/05/06/remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
I had the opportunity to spend the entire workday remote pair programming from
my office in Maui with a San Francisco client from <a href="http://www.cloudcity.io/">Cloud City Development</a>. We
used our normal tools of <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine</a>, Chrome, and iTerm2 on a 27&#8221; Cinema Display
shared via <a href="http://screenhero.com/">Screenhero</a>. While remote will probably never be 100% as good as true
in-person pairing, it&#8217;s getting very close! Here&#8217;s some tips for effective
remote pair programming. Scroll down to the bottom for the TLDR if you&#8217;re short
on time. Overall, I would highly recommend remote pairing with RubyMine on a
full 27&#8221; Cinema Display, using an iPad with a Google Hangout for eye contact!
</p>




<p>
Here&#8217;s a very detailed video of how to do remote collaboration:
</p>




<p>
<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/FkDhVrFgZAQ "></iframe></div>
</p>




<div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-1">Telepresence Using Video Chat on iPad</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1">
<p>
Per the recommendation of <a href="https://twitter.com/timocratic">Tim Connor</a> of <a href="http://www.cloudcity.io/">Cloud City Development</a>, I started using
an iPad for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telepresence">telepresence</a> for <b>only the video</b>, using <b><a href="http://www.google.com/+/learnmore/hangouts/">Google Hangouts</a></b>, muting
the microphone on the Hangout, and using the audio on <a href="http://screenhero.com/">Screenhero</a>. While one can
run Google Hangouts on the laptop, it can really suck up the CPU. Note, an
iPhone or probably an Android phone or table would work equally as well. In
terms of the audio, the microphone and speakers are better on the computer. If
one is using the laptop for the telepresence video, and using multiple screens,
it&#8217;s key to use the camera on the screen where one will be looking at the
Hangout, and not at the Screenhero screen. As shown from the below pictures,
it&#8217;s key that it&#8217;s obvious when the pairing partners are looking at each other
versus at Screenhero. Incidentally, Screenhero did not suffer from any
degradation when combined with the Google Hangout, regardless of using the
Hangout on the laptop or mobile device.
</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>
In the below images, note where our eyes are focused.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-sec-1-1" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-1-1">Talking to each other, making eye contact</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1">
<p>
<img src="/images/2014-05-06-remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/pair-programming-justin-steve-1.jpg">
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-1-2" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-1-2">Both looking at screen</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-2">
<p>
<img src="/images/2014-05-06-remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/pair-programming-justin-steve-2.jpg">
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-1-3" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-1-3">Talking to each other, making eye contact</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-3">
<p>
<img src="/images/2014-05-06-remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/pair-programming-justin-steve-3.jpg">
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-sec-1-4" class="outline-3">
<h3 id="sec-1-4">Shaka from Steve and Justin</h3>
<div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-4">
<p>
<img src="/images/2014-05-06-remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/pair-programming-justin-steve-4.jpg">
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-2">Screenhero</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2">
<p>
We both used <a href="http://screenhero.com/">Screenhero</a> on Macs. I&#8217;ve done plenty of remote pair programming
using Google Hangouts, but typically only one person sharing the screen drives
the code. Screenhero allows true screen sharing such that both programmers can
do the typing and mousing. With the shared screen being a 27&#8221; Cinema display, I
set my Screenhero window to <i>full screen</i> and the resolution was nearly perfect.
Yes, when scrolling and switching apps, there is a slight delay, but it was
extremely manageable to the point that I almost would forget that I&#8217;m working on
a computer 3000 miles away. Although there&#8217;s a slight slowness in seeing keys
that you type, it&#8217;s minor enough that it&#8217;s not a nuisance. The dual cursor
support works great. Here&#8217;s a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_BojQaD64GU">video demo of the dual cursor support</a>.
</p>

<p>
<img src="/images/2014-05-06-remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/rubymine-screenhero-dual-cursors.jpg">
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-3">RubyMine IDE</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3">
<p>
Both I and my pairing partners were already using <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine</a>, so using RubyMine
was a natural choice over trying to pair with the conventional remote pairing
setup of tmux and Vim. RubyMine combined with Screenhero, the same size big
screens, fast computers, and very good broadband resulted in a productive
pairing setup. One thing I hear about Vim setups is that pair programmers tend
to not customize their Vim keymaps. With RubyMine, that&#8217;s not an issue thanks to
a feature called &#8220;Quick Switch Scheme&#8221; which allows very fast switching of
keyboard bindings. I&#8217;m a Vim user (IdeaVim), and I would have been crippled
without my favorite RubyMine Vim bindings. I like the &#8220;Quick Switch&#8221; feature so
much that I made <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L57xOTXF78w&noredirect=1">a short screencast on this feature</a>, displayed below.
</p>
<!-- more -->
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-4">Fast Broadband</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4">
<p>
I use a combination of the fastest cable and the fastest DSL I can buy in Maui,
served on a load-balancing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/ZyXEL-Internet-Security-Firewall-Dual-WAN/dp/B0042WCFI2">ZyXEL ZyWall USG 50 Router</a>. DSL is far slower than
the cable service, but I still keep it for the one day that cable is not working
right. As an additional backup, I have a Verizon LTE tethering plan for my
iPhone 5, so the chances that I&#8217;m totally out of Internet are low. Here&#8217;s a
screenshot from <a href="http://www.speedtest.net/">http://www.speedtest.net/</a>
</p>

<p>
<img src="/images/2014-05-06-remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/broadband-speed-maui.jpg">
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-5">Same Big Monitors</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5">
<p>
We both used <a href="https://www.apple.com/displays/">Apple 27&#8221; Cinema Displays</a>. On the receiving side of the share, I&#8217;m
using a 2012 loaded Retina MacBook Pro with SSD.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-sec-6" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-6">Audio Setup</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6">
<p>
I use a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blue-Microphones-Yeti-USB-Microphone/dp/B002VA464S/ref=sr_1_1?s=electronics&ie=UTF8&qid=1399442515&sr=1-1&keywords=blue+yeti+microphone">Blue Yeti USB Microphone Silver Edition</a> mounted on a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Heil-Sound-PL-2T-Overhead-Broadcast/dp/B000SZVZ74/ref=sr_1_1?s=electronics&ie=UTF8&qid=1399442457&sr=1-1&keywords=heil+pl2t">Heil PL-2T Overhead
Broadcast Boom</a> with a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blue-Microphones-Pop-Universal-Filter/dp/B0002H0H4A/ref=sr_1_1?s=electronics&ie=UTF8&qid=1399442563&sr=1-1&keywords=blue+yeti+pop+filter">Blue Microphones The Pop Universal Pop Filter</a>. (At the
time of writing this article, the pop filter is only $25.22 on Amazon Prime,
regular price $79.00, totally worth it!). This is the setup I use for podcasting
so it&#8217;s more than adequate for pairing. I use the audio from the Display Monitor
(Cinema Screen), as that&#8217;s behind the mic, so as not to cause any echoing.
Naturally, this only works in a private office. In a shared office, it&#8217;s
critical to have a very good mic/headset combo or a good mic. The Blue Snowball
mic does a pretty good job of filtering out background noise.
</p>

<p>
I did a quick search on Amazon to see what&#8217;s available for headsets. If budget
allows (and if you&#8217;re spending a fair bit of time pairing), I&#8217;d consider the
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/V-MODA-Crossfade-Over-Ear-Noise-Isolating-Headphone/dp/B003BYRGKY/ref=sr_1_1?s=aht&ie=UTF8&qid=1399443063&sr=1-1&keywords=headset+with+microphone">V-MODA Crossfade LP Over-Ear Noise-Isolating Metal Headphone (Gunmetal Black)</a>
plus the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/V-MODA-BoomPro-Gaming-Headset-Headphone/dp/B00BJ17WKK/ref=pd_bxgy_e_img_y">V-MODA BoomPro Gaming, VoIP Headset Headphone with Mic, Black</a> as both
have a very high number of 4+ reviews. It&#8217;s suspect that with the right audio
setup, the avoidance of distractions for an in-office/remote pair combo might be
superior to that of the in-office pair combo. Please post into the comments if
you have advice on the best headset for pairing.
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="outline-container-sec-7" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="sec-7">TLDR Miscellaneous Tips</h2>
<div class="outline-text-2" id="text-7">
<ol class="org-ol">
<li>Use <a href="http://screenhero.com/">Screenhero</a> for screen sharing.
</li>
<li>Use <a href="http://www.google.com/+/learnmore/hangouts/">Google Hangouts</a> or Facetime on a mobile device to share video of each
other. Prefer that over using Google Hangouts on your computer due to CPU
usage of Google Hangouts. I really like the iPad mini with the Apple folding
cover. It fits right under the Cinema
</li>
<li>Use large screen for screen sharing, an tablet for Google Hangouts.
</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t be afraid to try your regular tools, such as <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine</a>.
</li>
<li>Use fast broadband, fast Macs, same size monitors.
</li>
<li>A good audio setup is well worth it.
</li>
<li>If the computer sharing the desktop has multiple monitors enabled, then the
remote sharing viewer might not be able to use command-tab to switch
applications. This problem went away when there was only one monitor on the
computer doing the sharing. It might depend upon whether the cmd-tab is
showing on the shared screen.
</li>
<li>If using RubyMine, install your pair&#8217;s keybinding into your RubyMine
preferences. You can copy the keybinding xml file located in
<code>~/Library/Preferences/RubyMine60/keymaps</code> and then restart RubyMine.
</li>
<li>Consider putting Screenhero in Full Screen mode to avoid any compression of
the window pixels. This is especially important when trying to click or drag
on the remote machine, such as resizing the chrome inspector area.
</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t forget to take a break for water, stretch, etc. every so often!
</li>
</ol>

<p>
Finally, click here for <a href="http://theoatmeal.com/comics/working_home">OMG, LOL, on an alternative reality of working from home</a>.
</p>

<p>
<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/_BojQaD64GU "></iframe></div>
</p>

<p>
<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/L57xOTXF78w "></iframe></div>
</p>
</div>
</div>


<div id="discourse-comments"></div>


<script type="text/javascript">
  var discourseUrl = "http://forum.shakacode.com/",
      discourseEmbedUrl = "http://www.railsonmaui.com//blog/2014/05/06/remote-pair-programming-tips-using-screenhero/";
  (function() {
    var d = document.createElement('script'); d.type = 'text/javascript'; d.async = true;
      d.src = discourseUrl + 'javascripts/embed.js';
    (document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(d);
  })();
</script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
